YU CAO

Rutgers Department of Linguistics 18 Seminary Place New Brunswick, New Jersey 08901-1184 https://pterosdiacos.github.io/ yc825@linguistics.rutgers.edu

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

Linguistics Ph.D. student in linguistics specialized in computational linguistics, semantics, syntax-semantics interface, and discourse analysis. Strong critical-thinking and problem-solving skills.

Computation 10+ years of experiences in algorithms and data structure. The First Prize in National Olympiad in Informatics in Provinces 2007, China.

NLP/NLU Research focusing on how machine learning models and formal theories inform each other. Relevant coursework: NLU and Computational Semantics, Project Seminar: Linguistic Knowledge in Reusable Sentence Encoders at NYU. Graph formalisms for meaning representations at NASSLLI 2018, CMU. Statistical NLP (Coursera), Machine Learning (Coursera), Introduction to Deep Learning (Coursera), Bayesian Methods for Machine Learning (Coursera).

EXPERIENCE

• Ontology Linguist

08/2019-10/2019

Assistant XFN Group, Facebook (via PRO Unlimited)

Prototyped machine learning models for cross-domain semantic parsing. Automated inferences in OWL 2 web ontology and sub-ontology extraction.

• Teaching Assistant/Course Instructor

09/2018-present

Linguistics Department, Rutgers University

Course taught: *Introduction to Linguistic Theory*, *Invented Languages*.

• **Graduate Fellow** 09/2016–09/2018 Linguistics Department, Rutgers University

• Research Assistant 12/2014-07/2015

Center for Sign Linguistics and Deaf Studies, CUHK

Provided linguistic expertise and assisted in developing a Chinese grammatical knowledge assessment software for deaf/hard of hearing children.

EDUCATION

• Ph.D. in Linguistics

2016-present

Rutgers University–New Brunswick.

• M.A. in Chinese Linguistics and Language Acquisition

2013-2014

The Chinese University of Hong Kong. Dean's List. Best M.A. Thesis Award.

• B.A. in Teaching Chinese as a Foreign Language

2009-2013

Sichuan Normal University, China.

Distinguished Thesis Award.

PROJECTS

- Graph Representation of Meaning
 Revised Abstract Meaning Representation to model plurality and quantification in natural language
 semantics. Developed a semantic parser based on CCG and hyperedge replacement algebra.
- Investigating BERT's Knowledge of Language: Five Analysis Methods with NPIs.
 Proceedings of EMNLP 2019.
 Team project role: constructed and conducted transfer learning experiments.
- Automated Fact-Value Distinction in Court Opinions
 European Journal of Law and Economics. With Daniel Chen and Elliot Ash.

 Showed in application that the value segments of opinions are more informative of the ideological direction of U.S. circuit court opinions.
- Incremental topological sorting
 Designed algorithms for topological sorting with disjunctive precedence conditions. Experimented with different dynamic updating strategies.

SKILLS

Machine learning modeling in NLP Linguistic data analysis Python, C, Matlab, PyTorch, Tensorflow, Scikit-learn Statistics

LANGUAGES

Mandarin (native), English (fluent), Japanese (working fluency; certified JLPT Level N1), Cantonese (limited fluency), French (beginner), Hong Kong Sign Language (beginner).